- All right, I think we have a few people walking in now.
But thank you so much for joining this afternoon,
particularly after lunch.
We know there are a lot of panels happening,
but we're excited to welcome you
to our Pathways with Purpose panel.
My name is Kirsten Lundgren.
I am the director of Post-Secondary
and Workforce Initiatives at the Kapor Foundation.
We're located just up the road in Oakland, California,
but all of our work is really centered
around building inclusive tech ecosystems
in California and nationally.
And we thought we would bring together
some of our favorite university partners
for this conversation.
So they'll be introducing themselves shortly,
but to have a conversation that we feel is urgent
around the need for a talent-based form of students
and learners and workers that are interested
and dedicated to building technology,
especially around AI,
that serves our communities and everyone in them.
So particularly at the Kapor Foundation,
we are tracking every day
how AI is quickly reshaping,
particularly entry level roles and skill sets.
And while there's legitimate concern
around some skills displacement,
we firmly believe
that there's amazing opportunity
for new skills and new roles,
especially around AI ethics, audit, auditing,
engineering skill,
at the intersection of responsible design,
and that this is going to be increasingly critical
in a world in which regulation
and guidelines, guardrails,
for new technologies are up in the air.
So without further ado,
and we'd love to,
we'll have half an hour of just commentary
with our panelists and then we'll open it up
for conversation with you all.
We'd love to have this just be as interactive as possible
after a long day of other events.
But without further ado,
I'll ask our esteemed panelists
to introduce themselves.
If you could start with who you are, what you do,
what your role is,
maybe just a bit about how you, yourself,
have entered into responsible
pathway work professionally.
- I go first?
- Yeah. - Sure.
- Hi everyone.
Can you hear me? - [Speaker] Yeah.
- Excellent.
My name is Meredith Lee.
I am the head of strategic partnerships
and chief technical advisor
to the dean at UC Berkeley's New College
of Computing, Data Science and Society.
I have practiced to be able to say that in one breath.
(people laughing)
It's a very long title, but every word is important.
And I think really on a day-to-day
scale of things,
what gets me excited about my role
is that I have the opportunity to really ask some
of the long range questions.
Some of these have been echoed on stage throughout the last
couple of days at this summit.
But for instance, what can we design and build together?
Often for us at Berkeley,
it's together with other institutions.
We love working with the Chancellor's Office
of the California Community Colleges,
across UC's, CSUs,
which are represented here today,
and with civil society organizations,
philanthropic partners, state government.
Basically, I think as head of strategic partnerships,
I get to partner with basically anybody,
which is super exciting.
I get to ask the questions like,
how will that actually work?
What are the key ingredients
and what might success look like
short term and long term?
It covers research, education, and public service.
So it's a really broad mandate
and I think one of the things
that I've really appreciated is that,
because we are a new college,
the first in 50 or so years on campus,
there is this sort of vibe of possibility.
So much like we've heard from the students on stage,
love the AI skit, by the way.
You should watch
that recording if you weren't there in person.
There is this beauty to trying to co-create together.
Why I got interested in PIT, Public Interest Technology.
Well, I remember when it was called civic tech
and I am trained personally as an engineer.
I went into public service in DC
during the Obama administration,
having not done any policy whatsoever.
I had to pull aside a faculty member
who taught science policy and ask him,
what do you teach in your classes?
And can I get a little, you know, bootcamp
before I head over to the other side of the country?
And I think for me,
even though I love technologies
like from a device scale of things,
I like to know,
how is that built from an atomic level and so forth.
For me, it always started and ended with humans.
And so when the public interest technology
sort of movement and field came along,
I immediately identified with it
because I'd been working in that space
for a really long time.
And I think a lot of the questions we'll get into today
are about this moment where the landscape
for public interest tech
looks different than it did a couple of years ago,
and how might we inspire our students
to find their own pathways
to feel supported in having this huge,
amazing scale of impact,
in a slightly different landscape than,
you know, a few years ago.
Oh, you might wanna try this one.
- I can try this one.
Okay.
Hello.
- There's always a mic situation.
- I know, I know.
All of a sudden I have so many choices.
Hello everyone.
My name's Yingjie Liu.
I'm the director of Digital Learning Strategies
at San Jose State University.
So I lead faculty and student initiatives related to AI.
At same time, I also run
as a PI for state fund and as a funded
AI related initiatives
and also serve as AI advisory committee for our campus.
So that's covered the,
our policy and strategies to engage the whole campus.
So across all those initiatives and responsibilities,
it also helped me
to see the connections from innovation,
connect to the teaching, to the learning,
to the equity, to the public sector.
So all across.
So it's very interesting time
right now with AI actually help us
to build all the connections, connect all the dots.
I think that's lead to the question,
what drives me is really, right now,
even though a lot of initiatives
we are running related to AI
is to cultivate folks to understand what is the AI,
how to use it in a effective and meaningful way.
But at the same time, I think it really position us
to shape it in the way to serve our community.
And also I like to summarize it kind of like
AI shouldn't,
AI won't define the future for our students,
but our students will
and should define the future of AI.
So that's something our whole campus
is trying very hard to work towards.
So glad to be here.
- Yes, and Yingjie also,
could you say this too a little bit
about your background too,
because I think it's interesting, both you and Meredith.
- Oh, okay.
- Have these like technical backgrounds
and then you went into.
- Yeah, yeah, - This public interest.
- Thanks.
So my background,
I have a bachelor master degree in computer science
and then the PhD in cognition instruction
and the learning technologies.
So slowly you can see my path is like how to actually
bring technology meaningfully
into the teaching and learning category.
At the same time, my interest always
try to be the magnet, the translator,
the bridge either between the faculty
to students or between our campus to other sectors.
So I think it's very important for me at this time,
especially with AI going on how to demystify it
to make sure everybody on track at same time.
Really bring AI for for good collectively.
Thank you, yeah.
- Okay, is this working?
Yes, great.
Thank you Kirsten for the invitation
to be here on this panel
and I'm really excited to talk to you about these subjects.
So my name is Jess Peake.
I'm on the faculty at UCLA law school
where I run our International and Comparative Law Program.
And I come from this from a totally different angle
than my co-panelists.
I'm an international lawyer by training.
I've focused on human rights, war crimes and genocide
throughout my career.
I've worked for the UN and other organizations
and I've been on the faculty at UCLA for about 12 years.
And in the past five or so years,
I really became interested in the intersection
between technology, human rights, and accountability.
And so I've been focusing my research on that intersection
and I launched a digital investigations lab
at UCLA and co-founded
the University of California Digital Investigations Network
through which we partner with civil society organizations
to use open source information tech tools
and platforms for documentation and accountability
for international law violations.
And so I'm really a public interest lawyer at heart
and have kind of come to technology through that work.
And through this work, over the past five years,
I've met so many students
that are really interested in using technology for good,
interested in using technology for good in law.
But I came to realize that this field
was really under explored,
particularly in the legal academic setting
and we're really not doing a good job
of showing our students how they can enter
into these fields.
And that's what really got me interested in this area.
And I'm now a senior of research fellow
with the Center for Resilience and Digital Justice,
which is Safiya Noble's Center at UCLA.
And maybe you heard her give the morning keynote.
And so she and I have been thinking
through some of these issues and working in partnership
with the Public Interest Technology University network
over the past year or so,
in doing a study to look at how students
and young professionals are really thinking
about public interest technology careers
and what that means to them.
- That is a perfect segue,
because I would love to actually dive deeper
and have you share,
and I'm happy, do you wanna do the slides?
- [Jees] I'm gonna try and juggle.
- Okay, perfect.
That is so impressive.
So Jess is gonna share some slides about her research
called Expansive Vision for Pit Careers
that she's been doing at UCLA,
but would love to better understand
what students are signaling in terms
of their interest in picked careers,
what organizations they're seeking to contribute to,
what are some of the opportunities
and challenges that they're facing along the way.
- Sure, absolutely.
So as I mentioned, for the past year or so,
I've been a senior research fellow
at the Center for Resilience and Digital Justice.
And along with the Public Interest
Technology University network,
we've been working on a qualitative research project
to look at how students
and young professionals view
public interest technology careers.
And I'm just gonna put a few slides up here
so you can see some of the data as we go through this.
So between just after the election in early January,
before Trump was sworn in,
we conducted a survey
of almost a hundred students and young professionals
and asked them a range of questions around
how they're thinking about public interest technology
careers in this moment.
And what I'm gonna focus on today is,
is the really broad
and expansive vision that the students
and young professionals shared with us
for what this career path can mean to them,
even in the face of potentially changing circumstances.
So we first asked a question about what type
of public interest issues are you interested in?
And what the data shows us here
is that the students want career paths
that are justice oriented, that are intersectional,
and that really speak to their personal
circumstances and ideals.
And so what we see is they're interested
in a really broad variety of subjects,
from core equity domains like education,
economic justice, human rights, healthcare,
racial justice, and more.
They're interested in issues that come,
that are more policy heavy,
like healthcare, voting rights,
immigration, data privacy, and environmental justice.
They also have very community specific
or community centric concerns,
such as tribal sovereignty,
veterans benefits, and mobility exclusion.
And they're really interested in digital rights
and platform governance, including, of course,
algorithmic accountability,
surveillance and AI ethics.
And so what this tells us,
or one insight we can draw from this,
is that students are really not just seeking
to apply tech to policy,
but they want to use public interest technology
to address structural inequalities
and to repair historic harms
through their participation
in public interest technology careers
across different sectors.
Second, we ask them what type of work they're interested in.
And again, we found
that students are interested
in a really wide array of types of work
that really extend far beyond the reach
of traditional tech roles
or what we might interpret as traditional tech roles.
So, students are interested in research and analysis work,
from data science to investigations to policy research.
They're interested in advocacy and policy domains.
They're interested in community engagement and education,
including organizing and teaching.
They're interested, of course,
in the more traditional tech field
of product development and design,
including user experience, service design,
and ethical tech development.
And then they're also interested in more legal
and journalistic storytelling type work
that might involve civil rights litigation
or investigative reporting.
And so again, this is confirming
that students really see technology,
not as a standalone skillset,
but one that is going to be embedded in broader civil
and political work.
And they're really drawn to interdisciplinary careers
that blend ethics with storytelling,
with community knowledge, with systems thinking, and more.
Finally, we ask them what types
of organizations they're interested in working for.
And while there is,
of course, a strong interest in nonprofit government work,
a surprising number of students in the public interest space
also expressed interest in working at technology companies.
And I think this probably reflects a pragmatic response
to compensation realities.
You know, the private sector versus the public sector,
but also a fairly strategic mindset.
I think students today are thinking about ways
they can reshape technology from the inside
and they want to bring ethics
and equity into those dominant tech institutions.
And of course others are drawn to
where we might assume public interest students
are drawn to, like government, nonprofit, and think tanks.
But increasingly, students are thinking
about academia as well as a home
for public interest technology career paths.
So why does this matter?
I think it matters in this moment,
because public interest technology
is increasingly under siege
due to some changing political circumstances,
a lack of investment overall,
not just in this current moment,
and a lack of education, training, and career pathways
that are legible to our students.
But at the same time, the research is telling us
that young people want to do this work.
And so it's really incumbent upon us as educators
to partner with funders, with industry, with civil society,
and with government,
to begin to create those viable and visible pathways,
so that our students
and young professionals can pursue these careers
that they are already so passionate about.
And I'll leave it there and maybe come back
to some of this data a little bit later.
- I'm sure there will be many questions
about this rich data.
Thank you so much for taking the initiative
to dive in on this, especially at this time.
My next question is for Meredith.
I'm curious if you see any of this reflected in the interest
of your students at UC, Berkeley,
how you've then aligned academic pathways
across institutions.
Has this shifted academic priorities
and also just sort of the multidisciplinary aspect of this.
How has that kind of bled into your approach?
- Absolutely.
- I'll mix it up, but I'll try this one.
- Okay.
- Really appreciate the question.
At UC, Berkeley,
our new College of Computing, Data Science, and Society
includes the data science major,
which went from not existing,
to now being the most popular one on campus.
We had 2000 students graduating.
If you've ever gone to a concert at the Greek Theater,
you know that filling that Greek Theater is a lot of people.
We had to do it twice to fill all
of our undergraduate data science students.
And so you can imagine, just even selfishly,
if some portion of those students
went into careers in public interest technology,
went into public service,
whether at the state government,
local government level, or other options,
imagine what the cascading positive impacts could be.
So I love the theme of trying to, you know,
I wrote this down, reshape tech from the inside.
It actually echoes when we were getting
into federal government
during the Obama administration,
this call to reshape government from the inside,
go do your tour of duty.
It's not enough to just vote,
and you know, complain about the situation.
What might you be able to do crossing a bridge
to another sector, another discipline, etcetera.
So I think in short, the answer is yes.
At Berkeley we're seeing, you know, the continued trend
of our data science foundational class
feeding into 60 or more different majors.
Seeing the applicability
of the data skills, the AI increasingly,
literacy skills that were mentioned at the summit,
all going into a lot of different career paths.
I do have some numbers in case
those in the audience we're tracking.
I was asked, you know,
how many community colleges are partnering directly
with Berkeley along those pathways?
And our team is really excited
that there are 21 California community colleges
that have approved articulation.
Six of those were just in the last year,
for our foundational data science course.
And 27 California community colleges
are using our interactive computing infrastructure.
And so the combination
of things like a free online textbook,
where it's like, no pressure,
here's, you know, this material online.
By the way, it's been, you know, vetted from a community.
It continues to evolve with.
I see some familiar faces in the room
with leaders from the California community colleges.
That has been a real game change.
And now that we're coming up with the 10 year anniversary
of our national workshop,
I think some of those lessons learned
and best practices that
we saw in the multidisciplinary data science lens
are all the more amplified
and important in a multidisciplinary multi-sector
AI ready workforce frame.
So I'm really excited about seeing this data.
And of course, as a data science geek,
I would say like,
oh, and what might we do with the larger sample
and the 39 million Californians
and what could we, you know,
continue to learn together?
- Thank you Meredith, and thank you for pioneering
like all of this work,
especially on structuring pathways
that go back.
As a funder in this space,
we are very pro take, you know,
supporting opportunities in which resources can be shared
between university partners and community colleges,
all the way back to the K through 12 level.
So really exciting to see these numbers,
in particular, around those shared resources
that you've developed
and hopefully will lead to more conversations here today.
My next question for Yingjie.
So San Jose State University has been very well known
for developing some very innovative public
and private partnerships.
Obviously from Jess' research,
there's a lot of questions students have around like,
well, what does a career actually mean concretely?
How can I use these skills on the job?
If you could share a bit more about
how you've developed those partnerships,
any lessons learned, any opportunities
or challenges that you wanted to call out
for folks at community colleges, or otherwise,
who are trying to build similar opportunities
or would wanna work with the universities
to help build those opportunities.
- Awesome, great questions.
So at San Jose State,
I'm fortunate lead quite a few very fun initiatives
across the sector.
I'm gonna go through them one by one.
So for public sector, I was able to,
I have been able to working with the city
of San Jose for the AI upscaling program.
So we have co-developed the curriculum with the city
and we have conducted two cohort already
with 60 employees graduating from the cohort.
And we are gonna launch the third one next month.
So just imagine for me,
it's my first time
to collaborate with city.
At the same time, when you see the audience,
there are police officers.
They're someone from three women department, right?
So they're very eager to have the AI skill
to help with their work process.
For instance 311, right?
So they have large data set
and they are wondering if their AI tools
to help them process the data
and get the main theme, what are the top, for instance,
what are the top issues our team need
to focus on at this time, right?
So a lot of those things very hard for them
to do without AI.
Now they're able to save more hours
and then contribute their energy
and team effort to the top priorities.
So that's definitely one
of the very successful model we have been launching.
And also some state we recently maybe you have seen
that signed agreement through Citi and with NVIDIA.
So over the summer
we are able to launch NVIDIA Omniverse
digital training for the faculty.
We have more than 100 faculty actually go,
went through the,
the training where the media engineer
put together like live session,
talk about the ins and outs of either training
and also 30 faculty who are tech savvy faculty
who are Python ready, they actually get hands on.
Yeah, yeah, you understand what that means, yeah.
So actually gather hands-on experience to went through
the very extensive learning past
the engineer experts from media build for them.
So now all those faculty are very eager
to integrate those into their courses and research.
And just today I already saw my inbox,
I have three more faculty who reach out talking about,
they're not Python savvy,
but they're very interested in learning more
about this such opportunity,
try to maybe collaborate with other faculty
and integrate into the courses.
And it is very eye-opening for me to see with AI
you actually can have a larger skill
interdisciplinary collaboration.
I have never imagined art
professor actually are interested
in doing the digital training in this way
and try to use their training, digital training,
to launch like theater performance, for instance.
So it's very eye-opening.
And also, for instance,
business faculty, right?
So a lot of collaboration from the business.
I never think,
I always think engineering faculty are the first tier,
but actually business faculty also see the potential.
So a lot of potential there on campus related
to this type of industry collaboration.
And also our campus is Adobe Creative Campus.
So we have been using this opportunity
to really bump up our students' digital literacy skills
and I have a most very exciting report from our colleague
from career center.
They actually collaborate
with other key stakeholder on campus.
Last week, they launched what they have,
the name is called Jump Starting Digital Literacy event.
They brought nearly 3000 students
and 15 faculty together in two days.
So all the student went through the training together.
And also we have partnership with IBM
over the launch.
You might have heard about the IBM skill build.
So we are actually
integrating those opportunities into the teaching learning.
And we also launched a hack song
with IBM related to AI ethics.
So it's, yeah, it's very timely topic
and the students are very excited about those
very meaningful topic,
so they can work on real problem,
but very meaningful real problem.
So that's another opportunity,
Across the CSU campus,
we also collaborate closely.
One successful initiative
led by our faculty from school business.
It's called AI for social good.
This has been a very successful initiative as well.
Try to bring the technology into the classroom
so students can collaborate,
interdisciplinary collaborative project,
but for social good.
And now it's extended to the whole CSU system.
They just launched a very successful symposium.
All the students present their projects.
So that's another exciting.
I got excited bragging SGSU.
(people laughing)
Yeah, so, and another project, my own project,
so it's a collaboration.
It is as a, oh no,
this one is founded by California Learning Lab.
It's a collaboration with a very non-profit
organizations called Quality Matters.
Maybe some the faculty heard about that.
So the reasoning behind it,
the goal is,
for us, we are fortunate to have instructional designers,
for instance, on campus to help with faculty,
with course design, quality course enhancement,
but not all the campus have such resources.
So we are working together to create AI agent platform.
So eventually that will be a very helpful aid for faculty
with course design and quality cross enhancement.
So I think that's the bragging I have.
And for the challenges and the opportunities,
I want to share is
it's very important we have, we are,
solving the real problem together.
I think that's the opportunity will actually help
with any challenges we are facing.
But working with the industry in particular,
what I have seen is,
they might not understand how education run, right?
So they might say, I have this solution,
now hand it to your faculty, right?
And magically it'll be successful in the classroom,
but right, yeah, right?
So, but it doesn't run that way, right?
So we have to help them to understand in order
to be successful, right?
Their infrastructure, their faculty training, which,
and all the things need to be in place.
For instance, NVIDIA training, even,
just for industry training is different
from what faculty training, their need.
So I have to work very hard to help them to understand.
Just handing us the list of this training is not helpful.
You have to create it as a learning path.
So the faculty will see it meaningfully
how this actually contribute to their discipline.
So a lot of things like that I think challenges,
but because we are having the same sharing goals,
I think those are opportunity.
Everybody work very hard collectively
to solve those problem, yeah.
- Thanks Yingjie.
Thanks Yingjie.
That's amazing to hear that full list
and menu of options available for both students and faculty.
And loved it.
I think it's important to note that
that faculty upskilling piece is a critical piece
to all of this in order to offer these services.
And as funders we're also thinking about that.
In the interest of time,
I think I'm gonna combine some
of the last two questions I had.
But would love if you could maybe summarize
your key takeaway on what you,
how you think university partners
and community colleges can best collaborate.
What sort of resources, policies, structures,
need to be in place to help with that?
And then maybe one key takeaway
that you wanna leave the audience with
on how to really forge these pit
career opportunities moving forward.
Whoever wants to start?
- Yeah, can I show one more slide.
- Please.
- And again, I'm gonna try and juggle all of these things.
So apologies if I mess it up.
So during the survey we asked students which
of the following currently affect
whether or not you pursue public interest technology jobs.
Right?
And so the data is pretty interesting,
and of course, everyone's worried about money.
We all understand that
and probably as educators can't do too much about that.
But I think community colleges
and universities can do something about
a lot of the barriers that relate to the perception
that these career paths are invisible
or there's a lack of resources for support
or there's a lack of mentoring and networking opportunities.
And so we together can help fill those gaps
through partnerships with industry, with civil society,
and with government,
to provide students with more visible pathways
and on-ramps to these careers.
And so this research will eventually result in a report.
So you know, stay tuned for that.
But we make a bunch of recommendations
to these five different constituencies, funders,
educational institutions, civil society,
government and industry.
And I'll just highlight a few of the recommendations
that we have for educational institutions.
So one thing that we can all collaborate on,
which would be a relatively easy lift, I think,
is launching public interest
technology focused jobs boards,
career fairs, and employment partnerships.
That's, I think, you know, something,
that can be a collective effort together.
I think our students really struggle
with translating their educational experience
into concrete skills.
And so we really need to equip them with ways
to think about that
and be able to track the skills they're developing
throughout their college or university experience.
I think in the law school,
or in law schools,
we have a a clinical education model
and I think that's something
that could really be co-opted in the public
interest technology space.
So where we're giving our students opportunities
to work with partners on hands-on projects
where they're receiving practical training
and also education in how to implement some
of these public interest technology skill sets
into the workforce.
Obviously students need increased mentorship
and support to do this.
And so those are some like pretty attainable
short-term goals.
I think some more medium term goals
that we suggest in the report are reflect back
to what my co-panelists have already said,
which is this need
to really embed public interest technology
into general education requirements
to make sure we're exposing all
of our students to technology and society issues.
And those numbers coming out of both
of your institutions are amazing.
We need to do that across disciplines and departments
and not continue to operate in these very siloed ways
that tend to happen at universities.
And then I think we need to think more expansively
about how we credential people who are wanting
to go into the pit field.
I think one thing that we found
through the qualitative study and then some interviews
that we did were,
students were really just not sure
what qualifications they needed.
And so there needs to be careful thought put
into what does that look like?
Is there something standardized
or is it really not a one size fits all,
given the very, very varied career things
that they're thinking about.
So I think, you know, my takeaway
is educational institutions
and we all have a giant role
to play in creating these pathways,
but we cannot do it alone.
It really does need to be a multi-sectoral effort
between us, between funders.
We need to be talking to prospective employers
in government, in civil society and in industry,
about how to really create
and solidify visible on-ramps to our students,
so that they can do the work that they want to be doing.
- Oh yeah, go ahead.
- Always love a bonus data slide.
Thanks Jess.
(people laughing)
These are really heavy questions that keep a lot
of us up at night,
so it'll be hard
to do it justice in a short amount of time.
But I think, if I were to have a magic wand
and have resources to be able to get
from where we are now
to the trajectory that so many of us
in this room want to see,
I think there's an untapped opportunity to really
reflect on some of the nascent pilot partnerships.
I'm particularly thinking about ones where we, you know,
for instance from the California Learning Lab,
another shout out to them,
we're able to get faculty led,
very much staff and student engaged collaborations
for the first time seated around,
for instance, an introductory computing,
no programming experience needed course
with a social science lens.
I think there was this unique value proposition
where for the first time
community college faculty,
shout out to Lianey if you're in the audience,
also Folsom Lake and LA City College
and others all collaborating
around a shared vision for a curriculum.
And we're all piloting, teaching this,
for the first times together.
That's pretty unusual.
By the way, this was also, you know,
seed funded from the National Science Foundation
to partner with Tuskegee.
And I think there's this, you know, pivot moment
where you go from a pilot
and some really compelling initial results to,
well is it actually sustainable?
Do we have the capacity on staff?
Do we have the, you know, infrastructure
and other sort
of just basic convening funds, like this convening is great,
you can't substitute for in-person connection,
but have we actually put
that line item in the requested budget to be able
to scaffold around the pilot
and try to take those lessons learned, best practices,
and really leverage that.
I have no desire to reinvent the wheel.
I hope that other people in the education space also feel
that way because time is short
and we don't have, you know, that luxury of just like,
I am only going to do this because I invented it.
I think we need to learn from each other's
experiences and contextualize for our own students.
And to do that there's simple things like, you know,
having a pathway for students
and faculty to get professional development,
mentors, resources and so forth.
And so often that is just others' duties
as assigned type of thing
versus something that we're actually asking for funding for.
Whether that's government funding,
philanthropic support, etcetera.
And so very much echo my co-panelists sentiment
that it's going to take creativity on all of us,
whether you're wearing an industry hat,
academia, civil society,
whether you've served in government or are curious,
all of those perspectives are needed
to really build robust pathways for students.
And if we can remember that it's about those students
and what they're going to do,
like our products as educators are students.
I hope we'll get further,
but it's going to take some rolling up of sleeves
to adjust to the current climate.
- Okay, thanks.
I will share, I'm thinking
for our university and the community college there,
and also public sector,
there's three things I want to quickly mention.
First is Shared AI Literacy Foundation.
So everyone is doing upscaling for students,
for faculty, and like I mentioned,
it's the city of San Jose, right?
So we should think together like
what exactly AI literacy we're talking about.
And so from the,
when we prepare the student
and also to the career path.
So we need to think our requirement.
At same time, for instance,
we just recently launched the AI literacy
course over the summer for all the transfer students,
for thousand students are enrolled into this course.
So if we think early, right?
So all the students are ready when they are transferred.
So I think that's definitely something
we can build up, the pipeline.
And also join applied project.
So for instance, the industry partner
for instance IBM over the launch, right?
So they're promoting the skill build opportunities
and we are promoting
and I think there might be opportunity for us,
just for the student to collaborate naturally
on tackling real world problem together.
I think that's definitely an opportunity
we need to let industry know we are interested, right?
So build those opportunity
and with the founder support we can make that successful.
And also for faculty as well, right?
So I just reach out to the California,
the community college, the AI fellow team,
I said in some of these state, we have fellows,
we have nine fellows, one fellow from each college
and you have fellow from divisions.
And yeah, with different expertise, we should talk.
All the fellows should talk and we should think together
and then contribute to each other's growth.
And I think that's, like I mentioned,
the AI is actually opportunity for us to get closer, right?
So because we are facing
similar challenges and opportunities,
we should do it together.
- Thanks.
Thanks, that's a great note to I think close on
and I wanted to open it up now to questions.
We have about 15 minutes,
so I'm happy to bring the mic to you,
but yeah, feel free to ask away.
Any burning questions.
Yeah, please. - [Speaker] I can speak.
Okay, great.
As I was listening to you I was thinking,
And I was thinking about graphics, and you know, sharing.
And how childcare was a very important.
How is it that we're incorporating our adults in agencies?
Because they won't have certain .
How do you see supporting them, helping them,
their trajectory, switching careers?
You know?
How do you support their needs and support them?
- The question is about how to support
a career switcher, career changers,
people who are trying to rescale in these pathways.
It's a great question.
- Yeah, thanks.
And others should definitely feel free to jump in.
I think what we've been thinking about
with this research in the report are,
how do we provide really holistic wraparound services
for all different kinds of learners, right?
Traditional students, non-traditional students,
those who are returning to education,
career changes, all of those people.
'Cause everyone's gonna have very unique needs,
but there are some commonalities between them,
with childcare obviously being, you know,
a very significant one.
And I think I to,
there's no easy fix to that issue, right?
Our colleges and universities are not suddenly
gonna be able to provide childcare support to all
of our student body, unfortunately.
Although if we could, that would be incredible.
So I think we need to think creatively about
how do we support those who have childcare obligations
or family care obligations.
How can we ensure the flexibility there
for those individuals particularly,
but also flexibility for, I mean, people can have all kinds
of reasons why they can't get to a certain place
by a certain time, right?
And so we learn so much during COVID about
how we can be flexible
and accommodate all kinds of different circumstances.
And I think there seems to be a little bit
of a push away from some of those accommodations
that were made during COVID,
but I think it's really on us
to think very carefully about that.
'Cause it brought a lot of benefits to a lot of people
and we don't want to lose that.
And yes, we, you know, being on Zoom a hundred percent
of the time all the time was not ideal.
But there's a medium happy place, I think,
that we can find between those.
And so we need to think creatively about
how do we deliver the content that we need
for educational programs in a way
that also accommodates the individual needs
of our learners and students.
- That's a great question.
I'll just add that I'm hearing a theme through a lot
of leadership discussions on our campus and other partners,
in re-imagining how and where education happens.
There's some great blog posts.
Happy to touch base afterwards.
I think another thing that,
particularly for public interest technology
that I've observed,
is the more that leaders in the space
can encourage students, learners,
from all stages to really feel empowered,
to not only learn, but immediately contribute
and, you know, own it, that you're actually innovating
because you're bringing unique experiences
and expertise to the table.
I think that can be extremely powerful
and in budget constrained times changing framing
and messaging is like a pretty, you know,
low risk thing
to try out and see if it helps in getting us
to the, you know, wide range of skill sets
that really make public interest,
tech and public interest, anything, successful.
- Blake, did you wanna go ahead?
Oh, okay, go ahead, yes.
- I'll stand up and use.
Perfect, excellent.
- So I'm trying to,
I'm kind of in the backdrop
of today's listening session.
The keynotes were powerful.
Kind of flipped a lot of my thinking on zero a little bit.
Hearing how this public interest technology as an ethical
and kind of using technology for good
kind of thinking, right?
And you were talking about sort of what are the pathways
to careers in this space?
And I'm just trying to,
I worked at a community college,
I'm a vice president,
I can help develop programming and degrees
and certificates working with faculty to do so.
And I don't know if, I'm trying to think through like,
is data science the thing we want to be doing here
and trying to elevate that in the program,
but that in and of itself isn't really gonna get you there.
Right?
And then how does then,
because you're trying to create this sort of catchall thing,
data science, ethical approaches,
I think ethnic studies, I'm trying to think, you know,
kind of good thinking we do in our humanities programs
that lead into everything.
So one thing, like I'm not,
what are your all thoughts in terms of how we could,
because we do like the here you go
and then you're all gonna pick it up and take it, right?
So what do you need here at this level
for us to kind of help you help our,
help us, help the society kind of engage in this this way?
Does that make sense?
- Yeah, great question.
Did anyone not hear the question about pathway development,
multidisciplinary, how to create the right type of pathway?
Who would like to take it?
- I can quickly share what
we have been exploring.
Right?
So I think recently we have
successfully launched, it's called AI Minor program
through the school information.
So it's a non-credit program,
and ethics is the requirement, right?
So, and a few other college are also thinking about
things like that, right?
So to pack those foundation,
like data science, for instance,
but on top of that you have to have ethics
and then there's another disciplinary related AI
technology course.
So you can pack things like that.
And then as a so solution,
I think that's what we have been exploring.
- [Blake] So like a Bolton instead of a thing, right?
If you could say, oh we're gonna create a degree in this
or I can create Bolton experiences to every group.
- Yeah.
- [Blake] And so I don't know if there's a.
That make sense?
- Yeah, go ahead, yes.
You can't end a panel without a little bit of spice.
- Exactly.
- Personally, you know, the, the debate
and wrestling around is this an add-on?
Is it a Bolton, etcetera.
For us at Berkeley, when we started data science,
we felt it was incredibly important to make human context
and ethics core to that.
And so it is a requirement
that every data science undergraduate
is taking and actually it's a super popular class,
human context and ethics.
And there's a whole pathway of like,
oh you found that interesting.
Like here's another way to explore that.
We have been discussing
with Safiya Noble at UCLA,
different ways to maybe offer UC, Berkeley and UCLA
and maybe community colleges,
if it's not bold and ambitious,
why bother is sort of our thing.
But like, you know, pathways where students could really
learn from the best of what there is to offer here.
So I think at its core,
whether it's called data science
or AI or technology, you know, for public benefit,
for us it's about empowering the data and AI ready leaders
with their very human perspective and purpose to go out
and do amazing things,
whether it's in health or climate
or education, or you know, technology itself.
And so yeah,
I would encourage folks in the room ,
if you're thinking about this,
to consider, you know, what is required, what is added?
And if it is, you know, an elective and added,
are there ways to frame it
so that people feel encouraged and it's not just like,
oh, and you know, once you do these requirements,
you have the option to learn about ethics.
- Yeah, I would agree with that.
I think that ethics kind of needs to be central to this.
And then what we also need to do is highlight
that connective tissue between how this then relates
to healthcare or justice or environmental work
or you know, racial justice,
whatever the subject matter is.
Because what my research has shown is
that students are really interested
in this broad spectrum of things,
but they don't always see
how technology slots into that.
And so we need to give them the foundation of, you know,
this is how we use technology responsibly
through an ethics course or similar, or courses, ideally.
And then show them how that connects out
to whatever subject it is
that they are seeking to apply it in.
- I would.
- Yeah, go ahead Yingjie. - Okay.
I will just add a quickly, for yeah, literacy,
the foundational AI literacy course we have built,
we actually have specific modules
talking about ethics and responsible use
and also environmental impact,
all those important topics
and the students' feedback, they really appreciate that.
At same time, they also value
the discipline specific AI career,
and skills, and knowledge, about that.
So another idea I want
to share is in the AI literacy course,
students have four modules, essential module,
the foundation,
but we also have the fellows,
remember the fellows are from each college.
So each fellow actually develop,
contribute college specific module.
So kind of like, here's a big idea about AI literacy,
but for our college,
what do we mean and what our career
and discipline actually need and require.
So kind of like help students see it,
you know, closer way.
Yeah.
- That's a great, that's a great question.
And as a funder, I think it'd be really interesting too,
like, 'cause we're evaluating models all the time,
but to kind of have a toolkit
or something that shows some case studies of this,
but we're huge fans of also modularized sort of learning,
but making sure that it's not just a box to check,
to Meredith's point.
So I think we have time for one more question.
Rick, did you wanna take it?
Okay.
- [Rick] Yeah, that would be great, thanks.
So one of the things that you guys are all from
before your colleges
and as AI is moving at this rapid clip
where people are paying attention,
last week, I'm already behind
and curriculum is incredibly challenging,
at least in it's coursework in a degree program that tends
to take really long,
even community colleges are really challenging.
So I'm curious about your take on the pace problem
for these programs.
And then the other point I wanted to make is that the,
that I think experiential learning,
especially of public interest, is really a strong model.
And I love the idea of having real world challenges
of discussions and conversations about that here.
And what I've seen is that a lot of people,
there's kind of the classic root of CS,
maybe maybe little data sciences,
as kind of becoming a specialist in AI.
That would be what most people imagined a year or two ago.
And then, a lot of business entrepreneur programs
are merging that are trying to apply it
and take the more entrepreneurial students
and nurture that with AI in there.
And I think this public sector,
or this public interest model that you guys are taking,
it feels like if you can figure out the pace problem,
having that as a third prong of it,
this sort of more pure technical,
the business entrepreneurial that could be greater
or it could be, you know, that happened earlier,
or the public interest,
which is inherently for good.
I really think is key to learning.
- Absolutely.
Anyone want to comment on this?
- I can't really comment on the time piece.
I don't think I have a good answer for that.
- You don't have an answer to the time piece of AI?
- I don't, I don't. - Oh my goodness.
I don't how we do that.
- It's changing every day.
But the experiential piece, yeah,
I think it's really crucial and key
and that's how we are going to set up our learners
for success in the workforce.
And I don't think that, I mean,
so in the law school setting,
when students are doing experiential learning,
they're doing it for like a semester
or a short period of time.
So it can be integrated in shorter time periods
throughout whatever period of learning you have, I think.
It's just a matter of, you know,
setting expectations with whoever the partner is,
of what is realistic to accomplish
by students in that time, right?
And that's something we run into in law all the time.
People think, oh, these students can come in
and solve this gigantic problem in 13 weeks.
Obviously they're not going to do that.
So we have to like break it down
and be very clear to the students,
but also the partners in what is going to be achievable
in that time and like what the feedback loop needs to be
and all of that stuff.
So it does need to be built quite carefully,
but I think you can slot it in into relatively
short time periods.
- Well, we learned in human-centered design thinking,
you can imagine if that problem were solved,
what would be different?
I think there's some lessons from agile governance work
where it was the same sort of like, oh,
we can't set up the regulations
and norms around governments
as fast as, you know, this is moving.
There's some interesting parallels there.
For Berkeley, we felt a huge pain point
when the scale of our classes
just really took off the student demand.
And in flipping that problem of scale
to an opportunity of scale,
we were able to come up with creative ways
where the faculty, you know,
they couldn't possibly do one-on-one, you know,
office hours with a thousand plus students,
1500 students, etcetera.
But groups where students who are just a year ahead,
or sometimes even six months ahead
from the current person in need,
that ended up being a very valuable scaffolding
that over the years you build up essentially this pipeline
of people who have been in
that student's shoes literally just recently.
And so I think there's something about leveraging our,
you know, creative students and how they're approaching this
and they, you know, have grown up in an age
of high paced, you know, interaction.
And so I think there's potential there that's untapped.
To your second question about experiential learning,
I remember as a student going to internships
and thinking there was something wrong with me,
because people said internships are great for learning
what you're good at and what you don't like.
And I liked all of my internships,
even though they were really, really different.
And so because we're living in this multidisciplinary world,
and you know, an AI world is a multidisciplinary world,
I think the more we can provide experiential learning
and let students know that there's a safe place
to explore in a cohort to, you know,
share their experiences,
it just makes it so much more real
and tangible for those students.
So yeah, I am a fan of experiential learning
and would love to discuss potential partnerships
with anybody else who's seen some
pilots in their individual institutions.
- Okay, I would quickly add one more thing.
I think as we talk about experiential learning,
it reminds me good teaching is good teaching.
Experiential learning is good no matter AI or not, right?
So it is good pedagogy.
And also I try to answer the first question about the pace,
you know, everybody need to be patient, right?
Because we are all working on this together.
At same time I think follow the lead of students, right?
A lot of time we naturally, as educator,
we think this is good for you, this is good for you, right?
So we keep adding things to students' plate at same time,
because we talk about the the future job,
all the workforce development.
At same time we talk about the entry level,
Java is at risk, right?
So we need to re-evaluate all those.
And then really put, again, back to the classroom
and think with the faculty, right?
So right now the course learning objective
actually should, based on the Bloom taxonomy,
we need to aim to the higher level, right?
In other traditional
we build, build, build, build, until that.
We actually need to flip, we aim high.
So that way when we prepare student graduate,
they have the skill ready.
But at the same time with everything going on,
we need to give us credit.
You know, everybody please be patient.
- Absolutely.
And it's funny as we've also seen some cases
where anything related to AI can get kind
of like best tracked, approved.
So some examples of that.
And then the last point I'll add just quickly
before we close is I think we really see it as a foundation,
like an opportunity to bring in startups
and the venture community into these conversations.
And that's why it's really ideal to collaborate
between universities, community colleges,
and that whole startup ecosystem,
because often that startup ecosystem is left,
you know, aside.
And I think that can inject some of that urgency of like
what is really market relevant,
as we saw a lot of students wanna to go work
for the private sector
and that's not the only option,
but I think that intersection is really key.
So I know we are at time.
Please join me in thanking these fantastic panelists.
(people clapping)
We hope that this inspires you all.
We'd love in a year from now to be back and hear
about some of the pilots that you have all started.
And you know, as a funder, again,
like we see other funders in this space
who are just very eager to see how we can help.
So we'll stay on stage for a little bit longer
and feel free to come up and ask any questions.
But thank you so much today.
- Thank you. - Thank you.
- Bye.
- Yey, we did it.